As a little Hawaiian,
كطفل صغير من هاواي
my mom and auntie always told me stories about Kalaupapa --
لطالما أخبرتني أمي وعمتي قصصًا عن كالوبابا--
the Hawaiian leper colony
مستعمرة "الجُذامِ" بهاواي
surrounded by the highest sea cliffs in the world --
محاطة بأعلى الأَجرَاف البحرية في العالم
and Father Damien,
و الأب داميان،
the Belgian missionary who gave his life for the Hawaiian community.
المبشِّر البلجيكي الذي وهب حياته لمجتمع هاواي.
As a young nurse,
كممرضة شابة
my aunt trained the nuns caring for the remaining lepers
كانت عمتي تدرب الراهبات المكلفات بالعناية بمن تبقى من المصابين بالجذام
almost a 100 years after Father Damien died of leprosy.
بعد حوالي 100 عام من وفاة الأب داميان بالجذام.
I remember stories she told
أتذكر القصص التي روتها
about traveling down switchback cliff paths on a mule,
عن السفر في طرق جرفية متعرجة على البغال،
while my uncle played her favorite hula songs on the ukulele
بينما كان عمي يعزف أغاني الهولا المفضلة لديها على القيثارة
all the way down to Kalaupapa.
على طول الطريق نحو كالوبابا.
You see, as a youngster,
لقد كنت في صغري،
I was always curious about a few things.
دائم الفضول حول بعض الأمور.
First was why a Belgian missionary chose to live in complete isolation
أولا، لم اختار مبشر بلجيكي العيش في عزلة تامة
in Kalaupapa,
في كالوبابا،
knowing he would inevitably contract leprosy
علما أنه سيلتقط عدوى الجذام لا محالة
from the community of people he sought to help.
من ذلك المجتمع الذي سعى إلى مساعدته.
And secondly,
وثانيا،
where did the leprosy bacteria come from?
من أين أتت بكتيريا الجذام؟
And why were KÄnaka Maoli,
ولماذا كان الكاناكا ماولي،
the indigenous people of Hawaii,
السكان الأصليين في هاواي،
so susceptible to developing leprosy, or "mai Pake?"
معرضين بشدة لعدوى الجذام أو "ماي پاكي؟"
This got my curious about what makes us unique as Hawaiians --
لقد أصابني هذا بالفضول حول ما يجعلنا مميزين كهاوائيين --
namely, our genetic makeup.
تحديدا، تركيبتنا الجينية.
But it wasn't until high school,
لكن تطلب مني الأمر بلوغ المدرسة الثانوية،
through the Human Genome Project,
من خلال مشروع الجينوم البشري،
that I realized I wasn't alone
لأدرك أني لست وحيدًا
in trying to connect our unique genetic ancestry
في محاولة ربط أصولنا الوراثية الفريدة من نوعها
to our potential health, wellness and illness.
بإمكانيتنا الصحية وعنايتنا الصحية ومرضنا.
You see,
وكما تعلمون، مشروع 2.7 مليار دولار
promised an era of predictive and preventative medicine
وعد بعصر من الطب التنبؤي والوقائي
based on our unique genetic makeup.
بناءً على تركيبنا الجيني الفريد من نوعه.
So to me it always seemed obvious
لذا بالنسبة لي بدا واضحًا دائما
that in order to achieve this dream,
أنه ومن أجل تحقيق هذا الحلم،
we would need to sequence a diverse cohort of people
سنحتاج إلى حصر مجموعة متنوعة ومحددة من الأشخاص
to obtain the full spectrum of human genetic variation on the planet.
للحصول على السلسلة الكاملة للاختلاف الجيني البشري على كوكبنا.
That's why 10 years later,
لهذا وبعد مرور 10 أعوام،
it continues to shock me,
لا أزال أصاب بالدهشة،
knowing that 96 percent of genome studies
لمعرفتي أن 96% من دراسات الجينوم
associating common genetic variation with specific diseases
التي تربط الاختلاف الجيني المشترك مع أمراض معينة
have focused exclusively on individuals of European ancestry.
ركزت حصرًا على الأفراد من أصول أوروبية.
Now you don't need a PhD
ولستم بحاجة إلى شهادة دكتوراه
to see that that leaves four percent for the rest of diversity.
لتدركوا أن ذلك يترك 4% فقط لبقية التنوع.
And in my own searching,
ومن خلال بحثي،
I've discovered that far less than one percent
اكتشفت أن أقل بكثير من 1% من الأبحاث
have actually focused on indigenous communities, like myself.
قد ركزت في الواقع على مجتمعات السكان الأصليين، كبحثي.
So that begs the question:
وهذا يجعلنا نطرح سؤال:
Who is the Human Genome Project actually for?
من المعني بمشروع الجينوم البشري في الحقيقة؟
Just like we have different colored eyes and hair,
فكما أننا نملك عيونا وشعرا بألوان مختلفة،
we metabolize drugs differently
فإننا نستقبل الدواء بطرق مختلفة
based on the variation in our genomes.
بناء على اختلاف الجينوم لدينا.
So how many of you would be shocked to learn
إذن فكم واحد منكم سيصاب بالصدمة لمعرفة
that 95 percent of clinical trials
أن 95٪ من التجارب السريرية
have also exclusively featured individuals of European ancestry?
أظهرت أيضا وبشكل حصري الأفراد من أصول أوروبية؟
This bias
هذا التحيز
and systematic lack of engagement of indigenous people
وعدم الالتزام المنهجي تجاه السكان الأصليين
in both clinical trials and genome studies
سواء في التجارب السريرية أو دراسات الجينوم
is partially the result of a history of distrust.
هو جزئيا نتيجة تاريخ من عدم الثقة.
For example,
فمثلا،
in 1989, researchers from Arizona State University
في عام 1989، قام الباحثون من جامعة ولاية أريزونا
obtained blood samples from Arizona's Havasupai tribe,
بالحصول على عينات للدم من قبيلة هافاسوباي في أريزونا،
promising to alleviate the burden of type 2 diabetes
قاطعين وعد تخفيف عبء مرض السكري من النوع 2
that was plaguing their community,
الذي كان يعاني منه مجتمعهم،
only to turn around and use those exact same samples --
فقط لاستخدام تلك العينات-
without the Havasupai's consent --
دون موافقة هافاسوباي -
to study rates of schizophrenia, inbreeding,
لدراسة معدلات انفصام الشخصية وزواج الأقارب
and challenge the Havasupai's origin story.
وتحدي قصة أصل الهافاسوباي.
When the Havasupai found out,
عندما علم الهافاسوباي بذلك،
they sued successfully for $700,000,
رفعوا دعوى قضائية وربحوا 700،000 $،
and they banned ASU from conducting research on their reservation.
ومنعوا جامعة ولاية أريزونا من إجراء بحوث على ملكيتهم.
This culminated in a sort of domino effect
وقد أدى ذلك إلى تأثير تعاقبي
with local tribes in the Southwest --
على القبائل المحلية بالجنوب الغربي -
including the Navajo Nation,
بما في ذلك قوم النافاجو،
one of the largest tribes in the country --
إحدى أكبر القبائل في البلاد -
putting a moratorium on genetic research.
موقفين بذلك الأبحاث الجينية.
Now despite this history of distrust,
الآن ورغم تاريخ عدم الثقة هذا،
I still believe that indigenous people can benefit from genetic research.
ما زلت أؤمن أنه يمكن للسكان الأصليين الاستفادة من الأبحاث الجينية.
And if we don't do something soon,
وإذا لم نفعل شيئا ما قريبا،
the gap in health disparities is going to continue to widen.
فإن فجوة الفوارق الصحية ستستمر في الاتساع.
Hawaii, for example,
هاواي، على سبيل المثال،
has the longest life expectancy on average of any state in the US,
تملك أطول معدل لمتوسط العمر المتوقع مقارنة بكل الولايات في أمريكا،
yet native Hawaiians like myself
ورغم ذلك فإن الهاوائيين الأصليين مثلي
die a full decade before our non-native counterparts,
يموتون بعقد كامل قبل نظرائهم غير الأصليين،
because we have some of the highest rates of type 2 diabetes,
لأننا نملك أحد أعلى معدلات الإصابة بمرض السكري من النوع 2،
obesity,
السمنة المفرطة،
and the number one and number two killers in the US:
والقاتلين الأول والثاني بالولايات المتحدة:
cardiovascular disease and cancer.
أمراض القلب والأوعية الدموية والسرطان.
So how do we ensure
فكيف يمكننا ضمان
the populations of people that need genome sequencing the most
أن السكان المحتاجين لدراسة تسلسل الجينوم أكثر من غيرهم
are not the last to benefit?
ليسوا آخر من يستفيد ؟
My vision is to make genetic research more native,
رؤيتي هي جعل الأبحاث الجينية أكثر محلية،
to indigenize genome sequencing technology.
وتوطين تقنية تسلسل الجينوم.
Traditionally, genomes are sequenced in laboratories.
تقليديا، يُنجز تسلسل الجينوم في المختبرات.
Here's an image of your classic genome sequencer.
إليكم صورة عن الجهاز الكلاسيكي لتحديد تسلسل الجينوم .
It's huge.
إنه ضخم.
It's the size of a refrigerator.
إنه بحجم الثلاجة.
There's this obvious physical limitation.
هناك هذا الحد المادي الواضح.
But what if you could sequence genomes on the fly?
ولكن ماذا لوكان بإمكانكم تحديد تسلسل الجينوم بسرعة؟
What if you could fit a genome sequencer in your pocket?
ماذا لوكان بإمكانكم حمل الجهاز في جيبك؟
This nanopore-based sequencer
هذا الجهاز الخاص بتحديد سلسلة ثقب النانو
is one 10,000th the size of your traditional genome sequencer.
أصغر 10000 مرة من حجم الجهاز المعروف.
It doesn't have the same physical limitations,
إنه لا يحتوي على القيود المادية نفسها،
in that it's not tethered to a lab bench with extraneous cords,
لكونه غير مربوط بمقاعد مخبرية بواسطة حبال غريبة،
large vats of chemicals or computer monitors.
أحواض كبيرة من المواد الكيميائية أو شاشات الحاسوب.
It allows us to de-black box genome sequencing technology development
إنه يتيح لنا فتح الصندوق الأسود لتطوير تكنولوجيا تحديد تسلسل الجينوم
in a way that's immersive and collaborative,
بشكل أعمق وأكثر تشاركية،
activating and empowering indigenous communities ...
وتفعيلية لجعل مجتمعات السكان الأصليين...
as citizen scientists.
كمواطنين في نظر العلم.
100 years later in Kalaupapa,
بعد 100 سنة في كالوبابا،
we now have the technology to sequence leprosy bacteria in real time,
أصبحنا نملك التقنية اللازمة لتحديد تسلسل بكتيريا الجذام في الوقت الحقيقي،
using mobile genome sequencers,
باستخدام محددات تسلسل جينوم محمولة،
remote access to the Internet
والولوج عن بعد إلى شبكة الإنترنت
and cloud computation.
والحوسبة السحابية.
But only if that's what Hawaiian people want.
ولكن فقط إذا أرادها شعب هاواي.
In our space,
في حياتنا،
on our terms.
ووفق شروطنا.
IndiGenomics is about science for the people by the people.
"إنديجينومكس" هو مشروع علمي من الشعب وإلى الشعب.
We'll be starting with a tribal consultation resource,
سنبدأ بمجلس استشاري قََبَلِي،
focused on educating indigenous communities
سيركز على تعريف مجتمعات السكان الأصليين
on the potential use and misuse of genetic information.
بالطرق الإيجابية والسلبية لاستخدام المعلومات الوراثية.
Eventually we'd like to have our own IndiGenomics research institute
وفي النهاية نرغب في امتلاك معهد بحوث "إنديجينومكس"
to conduct our own experiments
لإجراء التجارب الخاصة بنا
and educate the next generation of indigenous scientists.
وتدريب الجيل القادم من علماء السكان الأصليين.
In the end,
في النهاية،
indigenous people need to be partners in and not subjects of genetic research.
السكان الأصليون بحاجة إلى أن يكونوا شركاء وليس موضوعات أبحاث جينية.
And for those on the outside,
وبالنسبة لمن في الخارج،
just as Father Damien did,
تماما كما فعل الأب داميان،
the research community needs to immerse itself in indigenous culture
فإن مجتمع البحوث في حاجة إلى التعمق في ثقافة السكان الأصليين
or die trying.
أو أن يموت وهو يحاول.
Mahalo.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)